Hello, welcome to Career 247. I am
नमस्कार वेलकम टू करियर 247 मैं हूं
Prashant Dhawan. Now the world knew that the US would launch
प्रशांत धवन नाउ दुनिया को पता था कि यूएस
a strike on Iran if not today then tomorrow, but no
आज नहीं तो कल एक स्ट्राइक करेगा ईरान पर
one expected that it would do it in this manner,
मगर इस तरीके से करेगा यह किसी को उम्मीद
and it would do it so soon because
थी नहीं और इतनी जल्दी करेगा क्योंकि
Trump had asked for some time, they were evaluating it, there was
ट्रंप ने कुछ टाइम मांगा था यह इवैलुएट कर
talk that
रहे थे यही बात चल रही थी कि हो सकता है
he might have a meeting with Iran before the
कि यह ईरान के साथ एक मीटिंग करे बिफोर द
strikes, but suddenly the USA surprised the entire world by
स्ट्राइक्स बट सडनली यूएसए ने पूरी दुनिया
attacking so quickly
को सरप्राइज कर दिया इतना जल्दी अटैक करके
and the images of this situation room
की और इसकी जो इमेजेस हैं इस सिचुएशन रूम
when this attack was happening have been
की जब यह अटैक हो रहा था यह हाल ही में
released recently.  Here you can see the
रिलीज़ करी गई है। यहां पे आप देख पाओगे
USA Generals and Marco
यूएसए के जनरल्स पीछे यहां पर मार्को
Rubio is sitting behind them.  JD Vance is sitting here.
रूबियो बैठे हैं। यहां पर जेडी वैंस बैठे
Interestingly, let me tell you that the
हैं। इंटरेस्टिंगली मैं वैसे आपको यह बता
US media has reported that
दूं यूएस मीडिया ने रिपोर्ट किया है कि
JD Vance had told Donald Trump that in
जेडी वैंस ने डोन्ड ट्रंप को कहा था कि
my opinion Iran should not be attacked.
मेरे हिसाब से ईरान को अटैक नहीं करना
Israel would engage the USA in a war
चाहिए। इजराइल यूएसए को एक वॉर में उलझा
that we would not be
देगा जिससे हम फिर से कई दशकों तक नहीं
able to recover from for decades.  This was a warning from Jedi Vais.
निकल पाएंगे। यह जेडी वैस की वार्निंग थी।
Marco Robbio is also said to have the same
मार्को रोबियो भी बताया जाता है कि सेम
viewpoint.  Pead Hexeth who
इनका व्यू पॉइंट है। पीड हेक्ससेथ जो इनका
has a Kaffir tattoo on his biceps,
काफिर वाला टैटू है जिनके बाईसेप्स पे
he is being told that he should attack.  The
इन्होंने बताया जा रहा है कि कहा कि अटैक
US Generals were waiting for the
करना चाहिए। जो यूएस जनरल थे वह तो वेट कर
command to tell them
रहे थे कमांड की कि आप बताइए इन द एंड
what decision is to be taken at the end. US President
क्या डिसीजन लेना है यूएस प्रेसिडेंट
Trump, Nobel Peace Prize nominee Donald
ट्रंप नोबल पीस प्राइज नॉमिनी डोनाल्ड
Trump had to take a decision at the end. He
ट्रंप को एंड में डिसीजन लेना था इन्होंने
told his generals to attack and
बोला अपने जनरल्स को कि अटैक कर दो को और
after that USA took this big step,
उसके बाद यूएसए ने यह बड़ा स्टेप चला
everyone was nervous and now that this attack has
एवरीवन वाज़ नर्वस और अब जब यह अटैक हो
happened, the world is nervous to a great extent.
चुका है अब दुनिया काफी हद तक नर्वस है।
Nervous because we don't know yet
नर्वस इसलिए है क्योंकि हमें अभी पता नहीं
what Iran will do?  Will Spray of Hermes be
है ईरान क्या करेगा? क्या स्प्रे ऑफ़ हरमूस
choked?  Will Iran attack the US now
को चोक कर दिया जाएगा? क्या ईरान अब यूएस
?  Because let me tell you this,
को अटैक करेगा? क्योंकि मैं आपको यह बता
listen carefully to what I am going to say.
दूं ध्यान से सुनना मैं क्या बोलने वाला
If Iran attacks the US, then
हूं। अगर ईरान ने यूएस को अटैक किया तो
remember that the US is a NATO country and is
याद रखिएगा यूएस एक नेटो कंट्री है और
also the leader of NATO countries.  He
नेटो कंट्रीज का भी सरताज है। अनऑफिशियल
is the unofficial leader of NATO countries.  If Iran
लीडर है नेटो कंट्रीज का। अगर ईरान ने
attacks USA, in that case
यूएसए पे अटैक कर दिया तो उस केस में
UK, Germany, France, all these countries will compel
यूके, जर्मनी, फ्रांस यह सब कंट्रीज कंपेल
and the whole western world will together
हो जाएंगी और पूरा वेस्टर्न वर्ल्ड मिलकर
attack Iran.  Today we are
चढ़ाई करेगा ईरान पर। हम लोग आज के समय
at a very important juncture in history
इतिहास के एक बहुत ही इंपॉर्टेंट मोड़ पर
and world leaders are reacting in different ways.
हैं और वर्ल्ड लीडर्स अलग-अलग तरीके से
Regarding the US attack.
रिएक्ट कर रहे हैं। यूएस के अटैक को लेकर।
I will also come to Pakistan's reaction.
पाकिस्तान के रिएक्शन पे भी मैं आऊंगा।
There, Asim Munir, his government, his
वहां पर तो आसिम मुनीर उनकी सरकार उनके जो
journalists, everyone is in shock as to what has happened.
जर्नलिस्ट हैं सब लोग सदमे में है कि हो
Trump made a joke of us.
क्या गया। हमारा मजाक बना दिया ट्रंप ने।
But first of all I want to show you
मगर सबसे पहले मैं आपको दिखाना चाहता हूं
what reaction Narendra Modi, the Prime Minister of India has given to this attack.  Here
ने क्या रिएक्शन दिया है इस अटैक का। इधर
you will be able to see Modi ji's tweet.  It is being said
आप देख पाओगे मोदी जी की ट्वीट है। यह कह
that he has recently
रहे हैं कि इन्होंने रिसेंटली ईरान के
talked to the President of Iran.  When I'm
प्रेसिडेंट से बात करी है। जब मैं यह
recording this video like that.  Till now
वीडियो वैसे रिकॉर्ड कर रहा हूं। अब तक
PM Modi has not spoken to Donald Trump.
पीएम मोदी की डॉनल्ड ट्रंप से बात हुई
But now as you all know, when it is
नहीं है। बट अभी जैसे आप लोग जानते हैं जब
day here and it is night in the USA,
यहां पे दिन होता है, यूएसए में रात होती
perhaps it is possible that at night India may receive
है तो परहैप्स रात को हो सकता है कि ट्रंप
a phone call from Trump or the US Government.
या फिर यूएस गवर्नमेंट की तरफ से एक फोन
That will happen later.  But for
कॉल आए इंडिया को। वह बाद में होगा। बट
now, PM Modi has first talked to the
अभी के लिए पीएम मोदी ने पहले बात करी है
President of Iran.  This entire
ईरान के प्रेसिडेंट से। इन डिटेल यह पूरी
situation has been discussed in detail.  It is being said that the
सिचुएशन डिस्कस करी गई है। बताया जा रहा
President of Iran and the
है 45 मिनट तक ईरान के प्रेसिडेंट और
PM of India talked for 45 minutes.  Iran has
इंडिया के पीएम ने बात करी है। ईरान ने इस
also said in this call that look, whatever
कॉल में यह भी कहा है कि देखिए कुछ भी हो
happens, we have always considered India a friend
जाए हमने इंडिया को हमेशा एक दोस्त माना
and such things will happen in today's time because the
है और आज के समय ऐसी बातें होंगी क्योंकि
path that Iran is going on now,
जिस रास्ते अब ईरान जा रहा है ना वहां पर
somewhere or the other they will have to remind the you know countries that
कहीं ना कहीं इनको यू नो कंट्रीज को याद
see whatever
दिलाना होगा कि देख लीजिएगा अभी आगे जो भी
happens in future, you know, you should remember that we have always
होगा यू नो आप याद रखिएगा हमने हमेशा आपकी
helped you, now some people say that
हेल्प करी है ना अब कुछ लोग कहते हैं कि
yes we get oil from Iran, again look,
जी ईरान से हमको तेल मिलता है अगेन देखिए
India has not purchased any oil from Iran in the last six years
ईरान से इंडिया ने पिछले छ साल से कोई तेल
because of sensations.  We must have
परचेस नहीं किया है बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ सेंशंस। हमने
purchased many times more oil from USA
यूएसए से कई गुना ज्यादा तेल परचेस किया
compared to Iran.  India's
होगा कंपेयर टू ईरान। ईरान में इंडिया का
main concern in Iran, our main interest
जो मेन कंसर्न है, जो हमारा मेन इंटरेस्ट
, is the Chabahar Port.  Apart from that
है, वो चाबहार पोर्ट का ही है। उसके अलावा
we are not dependent on Iran for oil at
वी आर नॉट डिपेंडेंट ऑन ईरान फॉर ऑयल एट
all.  Yes, Iran chokes the State of Hermouse.
ऑल। हां, ईरान स्टेट ऑफ़ हरमूस को चोक कर
He shuts it down.  It
देता है। उसको बंद कर देता है। उसका
will have an impact on India.  So look here,
इंपैक्ट भारत को होगा। तो यहां पे देखिए
India has said that we are deeply concerned at
भारत ने बोला है कि वी आर डीपली कंसर्न एट
the recent escalations.  We want de-escalation to happen as soon
द रीसेंट एस्केलेशंस। हम चाहते हैं जल्द
as possible so that the
से जल्द डीएस्केलेशन हो डायलॉग डिप्लोमेसी
world moves towards dialogue diplomacy, but it does not seem
की तरफ दुनिया बढ़े आगे बट लगता नहीं है
that Iran will be able to do so. Iran will have to attack USA one way or the other. These attacks happen through
कि ईरान ऐसा कर पाएगा ईरान को एक ना एक
revelations, Hasbollah does it, they get the
रिवल्स करते हैं हसबुल्ला करता है ये
attack done through proxy or
प्रॉक्सी से अटैक करवाते हैं या फिर यूएसए
their people go and do something internally in USA, we do not know now.
में इंटरनली कुछ इनके लोग जाकर कुछ कर
Now we will see
देते हैं वी डू नॉट नो नाउ अब हम देखते
what discussions are going on in Pakistan, what are
हैं कि पाकिस्तान में क्या बातचीत चल रही
their journalists, senior most
है इनके जो जर्नलिस्ट हैं सीनियर मोस्ट
journalists discussing here,
जर्नलिस्ट यहां पे यह क्या डिस्कशन कर रहे
their government has openly condemned
हैं इनकी सरकार ने तो ओपनली निंदा करी है
this attack.
इस अटैक
Pakistani government was surprised that as soon as
पाकिस्तानी गवर्नमेंट वाज़ सरप्राइज्ड के
Asim Munir met him, as soon as he
आसिम मुनीर से मिलते ही सीधा जैसे ही आसिम
reached Pakistan, he
मुनीर वापस पाकिस्तान में पहुंचे
directly attacked Iran here
डायरेक्टली अटैक कर दिया ईरान को यहां पर
and at such a time, just a day before, the US
और ऐसे टाइम में एक दिन पहले ही यूएस
government had officially nominated
गवर्नमेंट ने ऑफिशियली नॉमिनेट किया था
Donald Trump for the Nobel Peace Prize, I
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप को नोबेल पीस प्राइज के लिए
mean I was laughing so much, it is not that there is a
मतलब मुझे हंसी इतनी आ रही थी कोई ऐसा
Nobel Prize in literature or anything, it is not that
नहीं कि नोबेल प्राइज इन लिटरेचर या कुछ
this man has brought so much peace
नहीं शांति कि इस आदमी ने इतनी शांति करी
in the world, the Nobel Peace Prize for him, the very
है दुनिया में उसके लिए नोबेल पीस प्राइस
next day Trump did bombing with B-2 bomber.  Let us
अगले ही दिन ट्रंप बी टू बॉम्बर से
give you a
बॉम्बिंग कर देते हैं ईरान की एक ऐसा
decision on Iran which was not taken before by Biden,
डिसीजन जो इससे पहले बाइडन ने नहीं लिया
Obama and even George Bush had
ओबामा ने नहीं लिया और इवन जॉर्ज बुश ने
not taken, so
भी नहीं लिया था तो पाकिस्तान तो
obviously Pakistan is in shock and this conversation is
ऑब्वियसली देखिए सदमे में है और यह बातचीत
going on in Pakistani
चल रही है आज के समय इन पाकिस्तानी
circles today. One problem in this for Pakistan is that
सर्कल्स इसमें एक प्रॉब्लम पाकिस्तान के
just a day
लिए ये है कि पाकिस्तान ने तो अभी एक दिन
ago Pakistan nominated Trump Sir for the Nobel Peace Prize,
पहले ट्रंप साहब को नोबेल पीस प्राइज के
now the reason for this was his
लिए नॉमिनेट किया अब उसकी वजह तो उनका जो
role in ending the war between Pakistan and India.
खत्म कराने में जो किरदार था उसकी वजह से
But you see
किया गया। लेकिन आप ये देखिए ना कि
how big a
पाकिस्तान जो है उसके लिए कितनी बड़ी
problem Trump has created for Pakistan, that a day
मुश्किल पैदा कर दी है ट्रंप ने कि एक दिन
before Pakistan nominated him
पहले उनको पाकिस्तान ने नॉमिनेट किया नोबल
for the Nobel Peace Prize, and he did not even wait for 24 hours
पीस प्राइज के लिए और उन्होंने 24 घंटे भी
and attacked Iran.
इंतजार नहीं किया और ईरान पर हमला कर
This line is being discussed a lot in Pakistan.
दिया। ये लाइन ना पाकिस्तान में बहुत
Trump has basically
डिस्कस की जा रही है। ट्रंप ने बेसिकली
used Pakistan.  Hee Fold
पाकिस्तान को यूज़ किया है। ही फोल्ड
Pakistan did not even wait for 24 hours.
पाकिस्तान 24 घंटे का भी इंतजार नहीं
As soon as this matter of Nobel Prize came up
किया। जैसे ही यह नोबेल प्राइज की बात
, Trump went in front of the media and said,
हुई, फिर ट्रंप मीडिया के सामने गए, बोला
yes, I deserve it.  Nobel
कि हां जी मैं डिर्व करता हूं। नोबेल
Prize: I have done so many good works, and
प्राइज मैंने इतने अच्छे-अच्छे काम किए और
I told you Trump is making a cover that after
मैंने आपको बताया था ट्रंप एक कवर बना रहे
seeing what I am going to do on Iran, don't forget what all I have done before this.  He
ना यह देखकर भूल मत जाना इससे पहले मैंने
literally used
क्या-क्या किया था। ही लिटरली यूज्ड
Pakistan properly and then directly launched a
पाकिस्तान प्रॉपर्ली और उसके बाद सीधा
big attack on Iran.  It
ईरान पे बड़ा हमला कर दिया। कमाल की
was an amazing strategy.  That means Donald Trump, I would
स्ट्रेटजी थी। मतलब डॉनल्ड ट्रंप मैं यह
say, works according to cut throat competition.
कहूंगा कट थ्रोट कंपटीशन के हिसाब से चलते
He does not care about others.  And I
हैं। ही डस नॉट केयर अबाउट अदर्स। और यह
think that other leaders will also understand this.
बात आई थिंक जो बाकी लीडर्स हैं वो भी समझ
Trump knows that no one
लेंगे। ट्रंप को यह पता है उनका कोई कुछ
can harm him because he is the President of
बिगाड़ पाएगा नहीं क्योंकि वो प्रेसिडेंट
USA.  So he will use all his power to see
हैं यूएसए के। तो वो अपनी पावर का पूरा
how he can
यूज़ करेंगे कि मैं कैसे बाकी दुनिया से
generate mileage for himself from the rest of the world and other leaders.
बाकी लीडर से खुद के लिए माइलेज जनरेट कर
Now here you people will ask me a question
पाऊं। अब यहां पे आप लोग एक सवाल पूछोगे
that ok, in a
मुझसे कि चलो ठीक है पाकिस्तान की एक
way Donald Trump has put Pakistan on an international basis
तरीके से इंटरनेशनल बेसिस कर दी डॉल्ड
and the Pakistanis themselves are saying
ट्रंप ने और यह बात पाकिस्तानीज खुद कह
that he has made a joke of it.  Did
रहे हैं कि ये तो मजाक बना के रख दिया। 24
n't wait even for 24 hours.  But Pakistan was
घंटे भी वेट नहीं किया। बट पाकिस्तान
not secretly helping USA against
यूएसए की सीक्रेटली हेल्प नहीं कर रहा था
Iran.  Look what Pakistan was doing,
ईरान के अगेंस्ट। देखो पाकिस्तान क्या कर
these people were assisting the US in spying on Iran's air defense
रहा था कि ये लोग ईरान के जो एयर डिफेंस
system.
सिस्टम है उसकी स्पाइंग करने में ये यूएस
This has been proved to a large extent.
की असिस्टेंस कर रहे थे। ये बात काफी हद
If you look at the
तक प्रूव हो चुकी है। कई आप अगर जो ओपन
posts of Open Source Intelligence Network,
सोर्स इंटेलिजेंस नेटवर्क के जो पोस्ट है
they have
उसको आप देखोगे उन्होंने कैटेगोरिकली
explained categorically how Pakistan
समझाया है कि किस तरीके से पाकिस्तान ने
quietly gave entry to USA's BACN, Battlefield
चुपचाप जो यूएसए का बीएसीएन है बैटल फील्ड
Airborne Communication Node,
एयरबर्न कम्युनिकेशन नोड इसको एंट्री दे
in one of its countries and said that okay you can
दी अपने एक देश में और कहा कि ठीक है आप
spy on Iran.  USA has
ईरान पे स्पाइंग कर लो। यहां तक ही यूएसए
used Pakistan to this extent.  During the rest of the attacks,
ने पाकिस्तान का यूज किया है। बाकी अटैक
no details have come out regarding whether Pakistan helped the
नहीं आए हैं कि पाकिस्तान ने हेल्प करी है
USA.  I think Pakistan's Asim
यूएसए की। आई थिंक पाकिस्तान का आसिम
Munir was equally surprised that I did not
मुनीर भी उतना ही सरप्राइज़ था के मैं
even reach Pakistan.  Actually right now
पाकिस्तान पहुंचा भी नहीं। अभी एक्चुअली
Asim was meeting Munir Edwan.  I was meeting some other
आसिम मुनीर एदवान से मिल रहा था। कुछ और
leader.  Suddenly USA has
लीडर से मिल रहा था। अचानक से यूएसए ने
attacked Iran.  And Iran will
ईरान पे अटैक कर दिया है। और ईरान
definitely be very angry with Pakistan today.
डेफिनेटली पाकिस्तान से आज के समय बहुत
But I will
ज्यादा गुस्सा होगा। बट घूम फिर के मैं
say this in a roundabout way that Iran should also have thought that a
यही बोलूंगा ईरान को भी सोचना चाहिए था कि
country which can do all this with Afghanistan, a
जो देश अफगानिस्तान के साथ यह सब कर सकता
country which literally survives because of the help of USA, be it
है जो देश लिटरली यूएसए के हेल्प की वजह
IMF or World
से सर्वाइव करता है चाहे आईएमएफ हो वर्ल्ड
Bank, why wouldn't it spy for USA
बैंक हो वो क्यों ना यूएसए के लिए स्पाइंग
and many times when Iran raised the issue of Kashmir,
करेगा और ईरान काफी बार जब कश्मीर का इशू
they should have thought why they are
रेज करता था इनको सोचना चाहिए था कि ये
spoiling their relations with India
इंडिया के साथ अपने रिलेशंस खराब क्यों कर
for the sake of Pakistan,
रहे हैं फॉर द सेक ऑफ पाकिस्तान कहीं ना
somewhere I would say that Iran's policy
कहीं मैं कहूंगा ईरान की जो पॉलिसी थी
regarding India and Pakistan had a big
रिगार्डिंग इंडिया एंड पाकिस्तान इसमें
flaw in it.  They thought that since they are
बहुत बड़ा बड़ा फ्लॉ था। इनको लगा कि
OIC members and are Islamic countries,
ओआईसी मेंबर हैं, इस्लामिक कंट्रीज हैं तो
Pakistan will support them.  But the end is now in
पाकिस्तान साथ देगा। बट इन द एंड अब आज के
front of you today.  First Pakistan
समय आपके सामने ही है। पहले पाकिस्तान ने
gave intelligence input to USA.  Now when
इंटेलिजेंस इनपुट दे दिया यूएसए को। अब जब
USA has attacked, Pakistan is saying that
यूएसए ने अटैक कर दिया है तो पाकिस्तान कह
we had no idea.  We do
रहा है हमें तो पता ही नहीं। हमें पता ही
n't even know what happened and when.  And again, this post,
नहीं कब क्या हो गया। और अगेन यह जो पोस्ट
here even
है ना यहां पर पाकिस्तान की ऐसी पोस्ट
India has not made such a post like Pakistan.  Why?  Because
इंडिया ने भी नहीं करी। क्यों? क्योंकि
we never nominated Trump for the Nobel Prize.
हमने कभी ना ट्रंप को नोबेल प्राइज के लिए
Pakistan is
नॉमिनेट किया नहीं था। पाकिस्तान को
forced to openly condemn the
मजबूरी में आकर ना ओपनली निंदा करनी पड़
US attacks on the nuclear
रही है यूएस के अटैक्स की ऑन द न्यूक्लियर
facilities of the Islamic Republic of Iran.
फैसिलिटीज ऑफ इस्लामिक रिपब्लिक ऑफ ईरान।
He has said that if there is escalation
इन्होंने कहा है कि और अगर एस्कलेशन होती
then anything can happen.  The situation will get worse.
है तो कुछ भी हो सकता है। सिचुएशन खराब हो
International law must be applied here.
जाएगी। इंटरनेशनल लॉ को यहां पर अबेडल्ड
All these things have been done here
करना चाहिए। ये सब बातें यहां पर
by Pakistan.  But again it is too
पाकिस्तान ने करी है। बट अगेन इट इज टू
little too late.  Which is what Trump wanted.  Again
लिटिल टू लेट। जो ट्रंप को चाहिए था। अगेन
I told you earlier.  Trump
मैंने आपको पहले ही बताया था। ट्रंप को
knew he would not get the Nobel Prize.   All
पता था उनको नोबेल प्राइज नहीं मिलेगा।
he wanted was some
उन्हें बस थोड़ी बहुत ना कहीं से बस एक
international praise from somewhere which he could use
इंटरनेशनल तारीफ चाहिए थी जिसको वो यूज़
to tell his people
कर सके अपने लोगों के सामने बताने के लिए
that if I have done this, then remember that
कि अगर मैंने यह किया है तो याद रखिएगा
before this I have also done such work
इससे पहले मैंने ऐसे काम भी किए हैं जिसके
for which countries have nominated me for the Nobel Peace Prize.
लिए कंट्रीज मुझको नोबेल पीस प्राइज के
And now Trump will repeat the same
लिए नॉमिनेट कर चुकी हैं। और अब ट्रंप सेम
thing in his mid-term elections.
बात अपने मिड टर्म इलेक्शंस में भी
But again we have to see
दोहराएंगे। बट अगेन देखना होगा कि अब ईरान
what Iran's reaction is going to be.  Remember,
का रिएक्शन क्या होने वाला है। याद रखिएगा
if Iran attacks the US, NATO will get
ईरान ने अगर यूएस को अटैक किया तो नेटो
involved here.  So, there will
यहां पर इनवॉल्व हो जाएगा। तो अभी बहुत सी
be many developments and many updates
डेवलपमेंट्स होंगी, बहुत सी अपडेट्स
coming up.  I will keep bringing updated videos for you.
आएंगी। मैं आपके लिए अपडेटेड वीडियोस लाता
And finally a very important message for you all,
रहूंगा। और फाइनली आप लोगों के लिए बहुत
India
ही इंपॉर्टेंट मैसेज भारत को आज के समय
needs data scientists today.  That is why you must have noticed that the
चाहिए डाटा साइंटिस्ट। इसलिए आपने देखा
IITs of our country have also started offering
होगा हमारे देश के आईआईटीस ने भी अब डाटा
certificate programmes related to data science
साइंस से रिलेटेड सर्टिफिकेट प्रोग्राम्स
and the reason for this is
करने स्टार्ट कर दिए हैं और इसका रीज़न
very simple.  The global economy is now
बहुत ही सिंपल है। ग्लोबल इकॉनमी अब काफी
largely data driven.  Unless this
हद तक डाटा ड्रिवन हो चुकी है। जब तक ये
company has proper information about the data, the
कंपनी के पास डाटा की प्रॉपर जानकारी है
company cannot progress further.
नहीं वो कंपनी आगे तरक्की कर नहीं सकती।
And that is why you must have noticed that almost every
और इसीलिए आपने देखा होगा ऑलमोस्ट हर
startup today wants a data scientist
स्टार्टअप आज के समय एक डाटा साइंटिस्ट
and you have the opportunity to make a career for
चाहती है और आपके पास मौका है इस
yourself in this important global economy
इंपॉर्टेंट ग्लोबल इकॉनमी में खुद के लिए
by becoming a data
एक करियर बनाने का बाय बिकमिंग अ डाटा
scientist yourself as a data scientist the
साइंटिस्ट योरसेल्फ एज ए डाटा साइंटिस्ट
doors of the whole world are open for you,
पूरी दुनिया के दरवाजे आपके लिए खुले हैं
you can work in any company like ICICI Bank, American Express, Accenture
आप ICICI बैंक अमेरिकन एक्सप्रेस एक्सेंचर
because frankly
क्योंकि फ्रैंकली डाटा साइंटिस्ट की
you will find the requirement of data scientists everywhere and Career 247
आवश्यकता हर जगह आपको मिलेगी और करियर 247
brings you our flagship
आपके लिए लेके आया है हमारा फ्लैकशिप
Data Science and Machine Learning with Generative
डाटा साइंस एंड मशीन लर्निंग विद जनरेटिव
AI course.  We specifically
एआई कोर्स। हमने स्पेसिफिकली यहां पर
included generative AI here because today there is
जनरेटिव एआई को डाला है क्योंकि आज के समय
no such thing as generative AI.  Data Science and Machine
बिना जनरेटिव एआई के। डाटा साइंस और मशीन
Learning cannot be mastered and
लर्निंग में आपको महारत नहीं मिल सकती और
hence our online course will run for 6 months.  There
इसलिए हमारा ऑनलाइन कोर्स चलेगा 6 महीने
are 260 hours of live classes here.
तक। यहां पर 260 आवर्स है लाइव क्लासेस
So let's see what happens.
की। कि यूजली देखिए क्या होता है।
Most of the courses that are available online these
ज्यादातर जो भी कोर्सेज ऑनलाइन है आज के
days are offered by Google and Harvard for data science.
समय क्योंकि डाटा साइंस का कोर्स Google
Mostly
दे रहा है, हार्व दे रहा है। ज्यादातर
you will get pre-recorded classes and
आपको मिलेगी प्री रिकॉर्डेड क्लासेस और
their quality is also not so good.
उनकी भी क्वालिटी इतनी अच्छी नहीं होती
Where s when you get live classes.
है। वेयर एस जब आपको लाइव क्लास मिलती है।
You can talk to the teacher openly yourself.
आप खुद ओपनली टीचर से बात कर सकते हैं। एक
Through a webcam or a microphone.  You will be
वेबक या फिर एक माइक्रोफोन के जरिए। आप
able to ask the question immediately that
उसी वक्त सवाल पूछ पाओगे कि सिलेबस में यह
when will this topic be taught in the syllabus?  What
टॉपिक कब पढ़ाया जाएगा? आपको कौन-कौन से
tools do you need to learn?  You will be able to understand Pandas, Amazon,
टूल सीखने की आवश्यकता है? पंडास, Amazon,
Web Services, Jupiter properly
वेब सर्विस, जुपिटर इन सबको प्रॉपर्ली आप
and then of course, under this course,
समझ पाओगे और फिर ऑफ कोर्स इस कोर्स के
you will also do projects with us,
अंडर आप हमारे साथ प्रोजेक्ट्स भी करेंगे
which will help you properly understand
जिससे आपको प्रॉपर्ली समझ में आएगा कि
how to actually use the skills.
एक्चुअली स्किल्स का इस्तेमाल करना कैसे
So, what do you do here?
है। तो, यहां पे आपको करना क्या है?
Simply
सिंपली जो वीडियो आप देख रहे हैं, इसकी
go to the comment section of the video you are watching.
कमेंट सेक्शन में जाओ। कमेंट सेक्शन में
You will find this link to Enroll Now in the comment section.
यह लिंक आपको मिल जाएगा एनरोल नाउ का।
Click here.  This page will open in front of you.
यहां पर करिए क्लिक। आपके सामने यह पेज
Here just enter your name, email
खुल जाएगा। यहां पर सिर्फ अपना नाम, ईमेल
ID, number etc. and the discount code is
आईडी, नंबर यह सब डालिए जो डिस्काउंट कोड
obviously PG10 because if
है ऑब्वियसली यह डालिएगा PG10 क्योंकि अगर
you enter PG10 then you will
आप PG10 डालते हैं तो आपको एक
get a significant discount and you will be
सिग्निफिकेंट डिस्काउंट मिलेगा जिससे आप
able to save your hard earned money.  That's
अपना हार्ड अर्न मनी बचा पाएंगे। दैट्स
it.  You have to apply here.
इट। आपको यहां पर कर देना है अप्लाई। उसके
After that the Career 247 consultant will call you.
बाद करियर 247 के कंसलटेंट आपको कॉल
You can talk to them about the
करेंगे। आप इनसे बातचीत कर सकते हैं कि इस
eligibility for this course?  Is this
कोर्स की एलिजिबिलिटी क्या है? क्या यह
course for you?  And by the way, let me tell you that
कोर्स आपके लिए है? और वैसे मैं आपको बता
if you are a working professional.  Right now
दूं आप अगर एक वर्किंग प्रोफेशनल है। अभी
you are already working somewhere.  If you
आप ऑलरेडी कहीं पर काम कर रहे हैं। आपको
want a better job, a better paying job, then
बेहतर जॉब चाहिए, बेटर पेइंग जॉब चाहिए तब
definitely you should do Data Science and
तो डेफिनेटली यू शुड डू डेटा साइंस एंड
Machine Learning course.  It will really boost
मशीन लर्निंग कोर्स। इट विल रियली बूस्ट
your career.  Let me tell you that
योर करियर। मैं आपको बता दूं हमारे पास
mostly working professionals come to us.
ज्यादातर वर्किंग प्रोफेशनल्स ही आते हैं।
Because the one who has not got a job yet
क्योंकि जिसकी अभी तक नौकरी लगी नहीं है
cannot understand what impact skilling
वो समझ नहीं पाता कि स्किलिंग से इंपैक्ट
brings.  Who has worked somewhere once.
क्या आता है। जो एक बार को कहीं पे जॉब कर
Only that person knows that the
चुका होता है। ओनली दैट पर्सन नोस कि द
more skilled you are the better you will be paid.
मोर स्किल्ड यू आर द बेटर यू विल बी पेड।
So our Data Science and Machine Learning with
सो हमारा डेटा साइंस एंड मशीन लर्निंग वि
GenII course is starting very soon.  The
जेनआई का कोर्स बहुत ही जल्द स्टार्ट हो
first class will start in a few days.
रहा है। पहली क्लास कुछ ही दिनों में
If you want to
स्टार्ट हो जाएगी। अगर आप डेटा साइंस में
start your career in data science then join this
अपना करियर स्टार्ट करना चाहते हैं देन
course.  And on this note, the
जॉइ दिस कोर्स। और इसी नोट के साथ यह है
video ends.  Thank you for listening.  And
वीडियो का अंत। थैंक यू फॉर लिसनिंग। एंड
as I always say, may God watch over you.
एज आई ऑलवेज से, मे गॉड्स वॉच ओवर यू।